Preliminary Inventory of the Roy Pryor Radio Broadcast Collection, 1941-1942
Hoover Institution Archives
Roy Pryor radio broadcast collection,
1941-1942
XX650
Pryor, Roy
Number of Items: 57 phonorecords (5.7 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Relates to American neutrality in World War II, the Japanese attacks on Pearl Harbor and the Philippines, and the first weeks of American participation in the war. Includes speeches by President Franklin D. Roosevelt of the United States and Prime Minister Winston Churchill of Great Britain, and newscasts.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographial Note
Roy Pryor was a hobbyist who, from the mid-1930s until the late 1940s, recorded radio broadcasts onto transcription discs in his home. During the early part of World War II he and his family made a special point of trying to capture programs related to the conflict in Europe and the Pacific. As a teacher and dean of the Menlo School and Junior College, he used some of these recordings in class and made them available to other educational institutions.
Source of information: "Pryor Collection," Archive of Recorded Sound, Stanford University, available at http://www-sul.stanford.edu/depts/ars/collections/pryor.html, accessed October 23, 2009.
Related Collections
Pryor collection, Archive of Recorded Sound, Stanford University
Access Points
Pearl Harbor (Hawaii), Attack on, 1941.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.; United States--Foreign relations.; United States--Armed Forces.; United States--Neutrality.; Phonorecords.; Churchill, Winston, Sir, 1874-1965.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.
Container List
- Sound recording of address by President Franklin D. Roosevelt to the 77th Congress, January 6, 1941, #445; (4 records)
- Sound recording of address by President Franklin D. Roosevelt at 4th of July ceremony, July 4, 1941, #561
- Sound recording of speech by President Franklin D. Roosevelt on the torpedoing and sinking of U.S. merchant ships by Germany, September 11, 1941, #587; (2 records)
- Sound recording of speech by President Franklin D. Roosevelt on Navy Day, October 27, 1941, #625; (2 records)
- Sound recording of speech by President Franklin D. Roosevelt to the International Labor Organization, November 6, 1941, #632; (2 records)
- Sound recording of Armistice Day ceremonies and speech by President Franklin D. Roosevelt, November 11, 1941, #638; (2 records)
- Sound recording of newscast by Upton Close on U.S. relations with Japan and Russia, December 7, 1941, #672
- Sound recording of newscast by H. V. Kaltenborn with first report of Pearl Harbor attack, December 7, 1941, #673
- Sound recording of radio news bulletins on Japanese attacks, December 7, 1941, #675; (8 records)
- Sound recording of newscast by Gabriel Heatter on Pearl Harbor, December 8, 1941, #678
- Sound recording of local newscast after San Francisco blackout, and #680 Newscast by Fulton Lewis, Jr. on Pearl Harbor, both December 8, 1941, #679
- Sound recording of news report by Royal Arch Gunnison from Manila on Japanese attack on the Philippines, December 8, 1941; and #682 News summaries of the day, December 9, 1941, #681
- Sound recording of address by President Franklin D. Roosevelt reporting on the first three days of the war, December 9, 1941, #683; (2 records)
  Use copy reference number: xx650_a_0002802
  Roosevelt speaks about the Pearl Harbor attack and how America intends to respond. He says the Japanese story has copied the arch of Germany under Hitler and Italy under Mussolini, saying Japanese aggression in the Pacific matches aggressions in Europe and Africa. He does not know how bad the damage at Pearl Harbor is. Roosevelt calls for the country to be prepared for strikes anywhere, including on both coasts, but notes the country has been gearing up for war for the past 18 months. He calls for the complete mobilization of the country, saying it will be a hard and grueling fight. He portrays service to one's country not at a sacrifice, but as a privilege. He believes there will be plenty of food for the war, but that other materials--metals, etc.--will be needed first for the war effort. He says this shows America can never isolate herself from the rest of the world ever again. Comparing the Axis powers to gangsters and recognizing the obvious conflict with the Japanese, he says America will also fight Hitler and Mussolini because it would be bad to have the rest of the world controlled by fascists. KPO - 7:00 pm
- Sound recording of news summaries of the day, December 10, 1941, #684
- Sound recording of newscast by Fulton Lewis, Jr. on war news, December 10, 1941, #686
- Sound recording of Congressional declaration of war on Germany and Italy, December 11, 1941, #687
- Sound recording of newscast by Raymond Gram Swing on war news, December 11, 1941, #688
- Sound recording of newscast by Fulton Lewis, Jr. on war news, December 12, 1941, #691
- Sound recording of newscast by H. V. Kaltenborn on war news, December 13, 1941, #692
- Sound recording of newscast by Upton Close on war news, December 14, 1941, #695
- Sound recording of newscast by H. V. Kaltenborn on war news, December 14, 1941, #696
- Sound recording of newscast by Upton Close on war news, December 15, 1941; and #713 Newscast by Upton Close on war news, December 21, 1941, #699
- Sound recording of newscast by Fulton Lewis, Jr. on war news, December 15, 1941; and #703 Newscast by Fulton Lewis, Jr. on war news, December 17, 1941, #701
- Sound recording of news report by Royal Arch Gunnison from Manila, December 16, 1941; and #706 News report by Royal Arch Gunnison from Manila, December 19, 1941, #702
- Sound recording of newscast by Raymond Gram Swing on war news, December 18, 1941, #704
- Sound recording of newscast by H. V. Kaltenborn on war news, December 21, 1941, #714
- Sound recording of "Over Our Coffee Cups" commentary - News report on characteristics of the American people in an emergency, December 21, 1941, #716
  Use copy reference number: xx650_a_0002803
  This program is commentary on the ability of Americans to change and adapt to new circumstances, focusing on the new war circumstances. KPO - 9:15 pm
- Sound recording of news report by Royal Arch Gunnison from Manila, December 22, 1941; and #720 News report by Royal Arch Gunnison from Manila, December 24, 1941, #717
- Sound recording of address by Prime Minister Winston Churchill to a joint session of the U.S. Congress, December 26, 1941, #723; (2 records)
  Use copy reference number: xx650_a_0002801
  KPO - 9:30 a.m.
- Sound recording of news report by Royal Arch Gunnison from Manila, December 26, 1941; and #728 News report by Royal Arch Gunnison from Manila, December 27, 1941, #724
- Sound recording of news report by Royal Arch Gunnison from Manila, December 29, 1941; and #736 News report by Royal Arch Gunnison from Manila, December 30, 1941, #734
- Sound recording of address by Prime Minister Winston Churchill to the Canadian Parliament, December 30, 1941, #735; (3 records)
- Sound recording of reports of unsuccessful attempts to contact Royal Arch Gunnison in Manila, December 31, 1941 and January 1 and 2, 1942, #737
- Sound recording of the State of the Union message by President Franklin D. Roosevelt to the 77th Congress, January 6, 1942, #747; (2 records)
- Sound recording of radio address by President Franklin D. Roosevelt, February 22, 1942, #815; (2 records)
- Sound recording of speech by President Franklin D. Roosevelt on seven-point non-inflation program, April 28, 1942, #891; (2 records)